today I will show you a framework that
will make you want to become an Android
app developer the name of the framework
is Jetpack compose and it's the future
of Android development it is powered by
the kotlin programming language and is
very easy to learn and understand
especially if you are a react Swift UI
or flutter developer when you see the
code I'm about to show you you are going
to laugh at how easy and familiar
everything is the biggest thing about
jetpack compose in my opinion and why it
really changes the way Android apps are
made is that it does away with XML you
may or may not know this but when you
are making Android apps without compose
you need to use a language called XML to
describe the user interface of your
application for example to build the UI
of this screen you would need to write
code like this one which as you can see
is describing where the text the text
input the buttons and the switches are
this is only to lay down the UI of your
app you then have to use kotlin to
select those XML elements and give them
interactivity or you can use compose to
get rid of XML all together and build
ups using pure kotlin so let's take
jetpack compose for a drive by building
a couple of tiny apps on Android Studio
after creating an empty compose activity
and naming it compose test drive we are
going to be welcomed by this code as you
can see inside of the main activity
class we are not bringing an XML file
instead we are calling a function called
greeting the greeting function that is
using The composable annotation will
look a lot like a component if you are a
react developer or a widget if you come
from flutter The composable annotation
tells the compose compiler that this
function should convert data into UI
text inside of greeting is a function
provided by compose and when we run the
code we get this UI next we will get rid
of greeting and we will create our own
composable function called screen inside
of screen we're going to render a column
that will have a text and a button the
button doesn't do anything when it's
clicked for now and it will have another
text inside of it that will give us the
text followed by a material button that
we can click but that it does not do
anything yet we can customize the way
the UI elements look like by passing
them arguments and modifiers we will do
this by telling our column to Center our
items to be as big as the screen and to
have a vertical padding as well we are
increasing the font size of our text and
button and we are using a spacer
component to create a space between the
button and the text getting an output
like this and now it's time to make our
screen interactive to give state to our
screen we are going to add this line of
code to it here we are telling compose
to create and remember a value that will
change and to set its starting value to
zero then we'll receive the value and
function to modify the value this part
looks a lot like react after that all we
have to do is to display the clicks on
our text and then modify the value when
the button is clicked and we are done
our first mini app is complete and as
you can see the code looks great and
it's super easy to read and understand
for our second and final mini project we
are going to build a currency converter
between US Dollars and Korean one we are
going to use the same column but this
time it will have an outlined text field
a spacer and a text outline text field
will give us a text input that will not
have a value and won't do anything when
it's changed for now it will show the
user a numeric keyword and it will have
a placeholder that says US Dollars then
we have a spacer and a text that will
show the result of the conversion that
will give us an output like this one as
you can see the input is useless let's
change that by adding data to our screen
first we create our state and set the
initial value to an empty string then we
give that state to the value of the
outline text field and when the user
writes on the keyboard we update the
value in our state the it keyword is
special in kotlin and in this case
represents what the user wrote on the
keyboard we will also display it what
the user wrote on the text and as you
can see it is working when but as you
can also see when the user does not
write anything the text at the bottom
looks weird to fix this let's only show
the text if the value of the state is
not an empty string and that looks much
better and finally using simple string
interpolation we can take what the user
wrote turn it into a number and multiply
it by the exchange rate and we are done
we made our app interactive we got input
from the user and we learn how to
conditionally hide components the code
looks great and I am happy now I want to
hear what you have to say let me know in
the comments what do you think of
Jetpack compose did you find it easy
familiar intuitive let me know also have
you used it already any rough Corners
that people should be aware of I
personally like it a lot it is
declarative kotlin is nice and the API
is meant like Swift UI and flutter the
good news is that it is interoperable
with XML which means that you can slowly
migrate your app to it or just leave the
old screens as they are and develop the
new ones using compose just like Google
pushed kotlin over java they are pushing
compose over XML and that I think it's
very good for the future of Android
development even though it is fairly new
because the version 1.0 was released in
July 2021 there are many apps already
using it including the Play Store app I
haven't made a jetpack compose tutorial
yet but in the meantime if you like
composing how the code looks like you're
going to love Locker I made two free
courses that you can join right now to
become from a flutter developer one is
that for beginners where we learn dark
and the other one is floater for
beginners where we build a productivity
and a webtoon discovery app you can join
the courses right now by clicking the
link below they are free and you can
join right now click the link below and
I will see you there thank you for
watching as always
see you on the next one bye
[Music]
foreign